okay I hope that was not actively
harmful for anyone so I appreciated this
opportunity to sort of invite you into
an inquiry that I've been engaging in my
own practice which is around stories and
the nature of stories and how stories
occupy our lives we are occupied by
stories and stories occupy us and
they're just really fascinating there's
a wonderful quote by Muriel Luke I'm
around if I'm pronouncing your last name
right but says that the world is not
made of atoms but stories and to which
you might say well actually the world is
made of atoms but that's just one of our
favorite stories about how the world is
made and so it's this really fascinating
way to sort of look at the world to
evaluate the way that we move in the
world and so I thought first I'd kind of
talk about my story in the context of
stories so for as far back as I can
remember I was so just to give you a
little bit of even more background both
of my parents are professors both of my
sisters my only other two siblings are
also professors so you know stories we
didn't call them that played a big role
at you know the dinner table
intellectual discourse trying to make
sense of the world be it politics or you
know philosophy or whatever it was all
about whether or not you could clearly
explain what was going on in a way that
others could understand could you
communicate meaning right
and so for as far back as I can remember
I've been looking for a story that would
give me security that would give me
meaning that made sense that would
explain why I was so unhappy right or
why the world seems so insane and so I
would you know go on the internet and i
would go to Wikipedia and I would find a
philosophy or a political theory and I
would get really into it and I would
think oh great okay finally you know
this is it this is like you know Marxism
or con sheehan philosophy or whatever it
is finally I found something that can
really give me security and I would
imbibe that I would consume that as we
heard in the talk and eventually I would
come to the bottom of it and I would
feel actually no this does not give me
security this isn't enough this isn't
what I was looking for and I would
discard it now would go back to
Wikipedia and look for a new story right
and that went on for a while there are a
lot of stories out there you may have
noticed there are a lot of different
stories they're competing stories there
are people that really believe their
stories are that one story that one true
story and they're willing to defend the
truth the veracity of that story to the
death because for some reason that will
prove that that story is true and then I
found Buddhism in meditation and I
thought okay you know I'll try this
story see where it takes me and a really
fascinating thing began to happen as I
sort of engaged with the story of the
Dharma of Buddhism in that the more that
I practice the more that I did what
the story told me to do which was like
sit down and be silent and like painful
though it was observe my experience the
less I felt compelled by the stories of
my life the less I believed that they
could offer me any real security any
real happiness and so that's interesting
and then eventually the the story of
Buddhism began to began to self-destruct
like there's some almost internal
self-destruct mechanism within that
story itself and then it's like whoa
okay I mean I kind of prescribed to this
story it was really doing well I really
thought this was the one I thought this
was the story that was really going to
get me there and now it's kind of like
even that story seems to have no ground
and so that's kind of where I'm at as
far as you know my story of stories and
I'm hoping to leave a lot of time for us
to share our stories about the story
that I'm telling you so you can you know
there are whatever 50 stories that are
happening here about this story that I'm
telling you but just wanted to share
some other kind of reflections on
stories so you know we are swimming in
stories and we might not we might think
okay stories are like you know creation
myths and folktales but it's so much
more than that right it's like newspaper
store newspaper articles and blogs and
how-to manuals and Facebook status
updates you know stories that we share
with everybody even if nobody actually
cares like these stories that fill our
lives that communicate meaning that we
assert our identity through and in a lot
of ways a story is nothing more than you
might say like an account of something
right like what are all
these unpaid bills here tell me about
that or why is there something rather
than nothing tell me a story about that
or where do babies come from tell me a
story about that what's that story are
going to tell me and in a very real way
stories teach us what's real what's
valuable and even like what is possible
what is possible so they can either
constrict or expand our sense of
possibility through the telling of them
right and how many of us here have had
the experience of being told a story or
reading a story and all of a sudden we
have a new sense of what might be
possible for us or for the world and
then we act differently all right our
actions transform because of a story is
immaterial something that entered into
our mind and then became our lives right
like I'm here today here right here
because I like went into my college
library and like happen to pick out a
book and I read a story and then Here I
am you know the path of my life
completely altered because of a story
stories are unbelievably powerful
and so when we engage in an exercise
like we just did we might find ourselves
sort of or we might notice that we are
compulsively telling ourselves stories
right about ourselves we're telling
ourselves stories about ourselves and we
can't really stop like we just can't
stop it's just like if if and if you if
you took if you actually really paid
attention there's a weird way in which
it feels really good to tell yourself a
story like you kind of get it's it's
serious it's like being a little high
you're like oh yeah okay and like you
weave this world and it's like this is
the world and it's going to work for me
and then and then what happens it just
pops and then you notice perhaps this
like oh like again again it's not it's
gone and i'm back in this like here and
we do this to ourselves like over and
over and over again and it becomes it
begins to become kind of hilarious you
know it's like yeah that's just kind of
funny i mean what can you do but laugh
at it you know we're just spinning these
stories that about anything right i
think is really interesting so this word
samsara right this it's a Buddhist term
for like this world of suffering but the
literal translation of it is uh going
around and around going around and
around right which it can feel like like
that is what it feels like if you just
sit down and like don't do a technique
right you just sit down you're just like
all right world like come at me right
and it's just you'll just find yourself
just going around and around and around
and around and around and you'll
rehearse like the same thing in a
slightly different way and you just kind
of do it again because you can't
you can't help it you do it again and
it's slightly different way cuz you
can't happen you drop it and you're like
okay this is different then you do it
again right that's just this going
around and around and around that's like
what it is that well hi why do we do
that to ourselves seriously like what is
it that compels us to do that it's a
real investigation on this path it's
like what is it that makes us do that
and so one of the things that Buddhism
and you know maybe mindfulness or this
spiritual path more generally tells us
is that yeah you know stories are here
we have to reckon with them but there's
one particular story that you really
want to look at really want to pay close
attention to you really want to like dig
into it with whatever you got which is
of course the story of the self right
around which almost all the other
stories we tell ourselves are sort of
constellated right we have this one sort
of master story that all other stories
sort of secure themselves by latching on
to you know the story of I'm not good
enough or I could never do this or I
need a new iphone in order to be happy
right all of those stories depend on a
self the story of a self and just like
anything else that we tell a story about
we notice that really is nowhere to be
found right like if you really look like
anything you're telling a story about
actually with your eyes closed sitting
like this it's not present except in
your mind except as the story and so in
these and so you know the Buddhism
really is trying to orient us towards
looking at this one core story and also
to drop all other views
yeah good too and so the problem itself
isn't so much stories but in how we
relate to them right this compulsivity
of being of engaging in stories of like
kind of being addicted to stories and
the really tricky part of it right is
that we don't even often know that their
stories right we don't even know their
stories they're just like it's like we
put on like a pair of tinted glasses a
long time ago and we didn't even and we
like have forgotten that we're wearing
glasses they're just like it's just now
the way we see things right and so it
can be quite startling to like take off
the glasses in fact you might want to
put them back on because you know it's
very it could be very different like I
you know maybe I can't I can't see
things the way I used to I like seeing
things away used to that's how I derived
my sense of identity and often a really
good teacher will go up to you and say
hey i noticed that you're wearing these
glasses you might want to take them off
and which we might say no no i don't
think i do and then you know the path
unfolds and so one thing i find
especially fascinating about stories in
the context of our work here at CML is
the relationship between stories and
what we sometimes call responsibility
here or what other people might refer to
as like social justice or cultural
change or maybe just making the world a
better place you know
so we don't just tell stories to
ourselves of course right we tell
stories to each other and we are told
stories by our culture or by you know
television by news programs and so the
task for us is not simply a huge though
it is to work with learn to work with
stories in our own experience but also
to play or work skillfully with the
stories that make up our shared reality
right and just like in our personal
practice a really interesting thing to
do is simply to question the stories
that are being told right so you know
for in my own practice maybe I'm
thinking you know and I'll just say this
because it's a it's a real story like i
really like a new phone right me i
really like that new iphone it seems
like that would be a nice phone tab
maybe it would make me happy to have
that phone i don't actually say maybe in
my head i say like you know that will
make me but and so then you know when
that story is playing in your head you
can say really you know if you have the
wherewithal you can say really like
really really is that going to make you
happy is that is that true I didn't have
to get an answer to it right you don't
even need to say no it's not true or
well might be true or something like
that just asking the question itself
destabilizes the story to the point
where it can start to fade away right
because most of the time that stories
are problem it's because we don't even
question them we're just like slaves to
them we don't even like think about it
right we don't even try to question them
we're just like okay story like you know
whatever you say I guess I'll go buy an
iphone right and millions of us do that
every day maybe unquestioningly obey the
demands of the stories we tell ourselves
not so different
culturally right so a great example this
that is I'm really interested in is like
turn on any news channel where they're
talking about economics right or about
national economics and they'll say
something like you know I have no idea
it's as accurate like gdp grew six
percent this year like her ray or gdp
grew two percent that wasn't so good we
really need to like grow more right or
they'll say you know we need we need
more production or more this never
questioning the story of growth right
nobody on nobody on CNN they're not like
you know talking about a jobs report and
like whether or not it means that the
economy is going to grow and they're
like well hold hold on now a second like
what if we're good how we are like what
if we actually don't need to grow the
economy right now right nobody ever
questions that story on CNN you will
notice if you if you see them doing that
let me know because that's that would be
fascinating to me but but you know or
another great story I was I was an
organizer at Occupy Wall Street right
and so a lot of stories got questioned
there one of the stories that got
questioned there was the story of
ownership right this very core story to
our sort of national mythos are our
modern world view and so to question the
myth or the idea the story of ownership
right that anybody can own anything like
what's that like you know that is a very
deeply rooted story and just in the act
of saying it's a story you know that's
very powerful because most people just
take it for granted they don't see it as
a story they see it as the way things
are just like the way we see the world
personally right we see things we think
the way they are but of course we don't
so the the fascinating thing about this
practice in relationship to stories is
that we see the ground lessness of them
all right that they aren't real in a
sense a very real sense they're not real
right and that very emptiness that very
unreality that very like Mirage like
dreamlike nature of stories implies a
sense of malleability it implies a sense
of that you can kind of do with it what
you want right and so it opens up an
opportunity for us to more consciously
tell stories to be conscious about the
stories we tell ourselves and to be
conscious about the stories we tell each
other and to toe and to be consciously
the stories we tell as a culture as a
people all right so um if the world is
made of stories to whatever degree we
see that or know that to be true the
world is made of stories then therefore
we can create a new world with new
stories that's a huge huge information
huge thing to know and so in the
endeavor to be more conscious about
storytelling this thing that we're doing
anyways unless you're not in which case
I would also like to talk to you are
they really interesting you know there
are some there are some questions that
we might we might ask ourselves and I I
want to end with some some questions you
know to to help us be more conscious
about our storytelling so
one question that I thought of was what
stories do I presently feel are the most
meaningful and wise
I don't know it's an interesting
question probably changes but it's good
to ask ourselves another question what
false and perhaps toxic stories from the
media or culture have slipped their way
into my consciousness short story about
this I find myself I'm 27 almost 28 now
and I find myself sort of passing
through a cultural gate as i call it
where it's like there are certain
stories about that for whatever reason
have been put into my consciousness
about what I should be doing at this age
and none of those stories involve me
sitting here doing this right so like
there's some tension there and I'm
realizing now I'm unearthing the fact
that like yeah I'm actually like this is
another layer that I've been programmed
or been you know yeah enchanted by a
story right a false story yeah so that
may show up in all of our lives in so
many different ways and it's one that
one thing is fascinating to me too is
how we're decentering the storytelling
from you know perhaps the mainstream
media into things like Facebook all
right we're telling each other stories
on that medium now what does that mean
you know I don't know but probably
something another another question what
story or stories do i subscribe to about
political change power or progress right
we may all have different stories about
that we can't change anything like
change is just around the corner voting
voting doesn't change anything voting is
the only thing that matters you know
it's it's amazing like the diversity of
stories that we tell about
is meaningful in terms of changing our
very sick society it's good to be
conscious about that to acknowledge that
that's a story and that therefore we can
choose a better story and then act from
that better story if we so choose if we
so choose and then the most interesting
question for me right now living here is
what stories do I want to live or what
stories do you want to live or set in a
slightly different way that that feels
more provocative to me what stories want
want to come to life through me what
stories want to come through life to
life through you maybe you have a sense
of that maybe you feel yourself pulled
by something by a story a beautiful
story that wants to come to life through
you good to know that
yeah I'll end with two quotes I like
quotes i found one is a from gary snyder
so poet you might say the world is made
of stories good stories are hard to come
by and a good story you can honestly
call your own is an incredible gift
these stories are part of a bigger story
that connects us all and this last quote
is by a lin yutang i like it it says uh
hope is like a road in the country there
was never a road but when many people
walk on it the road comes into existence
you